Finding Aid for Susan Wright papers, 1975-1982
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Susan Wright papers 1975-1982
Wright, Susan
2012127 Aa 2
Susan P. Wright was a faculty member of the Residential College, where she directed the Science, Technology, and Society Program from 1979 to 1997. Additionally, she was a research scientist at the Institute for Research on Women and Gender. These papers primarily document the debate over recombinant DNA at the University of Michigan in the 1970s and early 1980s.
2 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Material was donated by Susan Wright (donor no 9848 ) in 2007.
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open without restriction.
Susan P. Wright received her B.A. in Physics from Oxford University in 1961. She went on to earn an M.S. degree in Physics from the University of Michigan in 1963 and a Ph.D. degree in History of Science from Harvard University in 1975. She joined the University of Michigan Faculty as a lecturer in 1979 and received an additional appointment as associate research scientist in 1998 with promotion to research scientist in 2002. Wright founded the Residential College's Science, Technology, and Society Program in 1979 and chaired it until 1997. The program combines science training with the study of its relationship to society and culture. Her work in the Institute for Research on Women and Gender focused on rethinking approaches to arms control and disarmament. She was especially involved in research on national and international policies guiding the development of biotechnology. In 1998-1999, she directed an international project on biological warfare and disarmament. Dr. Wright received numerous awards, including the Rockefeller Humanities Fellowship, the MacArthur Research and Writing Fellowship, and the University of Michigan Excellence in Education Award. She retired from active faculty status in 2005 and was named lecturer and research scientist emerita.
Source: Proceedings of the University of Michigan Board of Regents, October 2005.
The Susan Wright Papers document the recombinant DNA debate at the University of Michigan during the 1970s and early 1980s through material collected by Dr. Wright. In the early 1970s, scientists discovered a method to combine DNA from different organisms, creating DNA sequences not found in nature. This led to concern that, among other things, the organisms possessing this recombined DNA could escape from laboratories and cause pandemics. A debate over how much this new technology should be regulated by the government ensued. Wright was involved in this debate through her position as chair of the Residential College's Science, Technology, and Society Program. The papers are arranged into four series: Ann Arbor Newspaper Coverage, Correspondence, Minutes, and Articles, Governor's Task Force, and Topical.
Subjects:
Wright, Susan, 1939-; Genetic engineering.; High technology industries--Michigan.; Recombinant DNA--Research.; Science--Social aspects.; Values--Study and teaching.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; University of Michigan--Research.
- Ann Arbor Newspaper Coverage
  The Ann Arbor Newspaper Coverage series contains issues from Ann Arbor newspapers and the University Record covering the discussion on recombinant DNA.
  - Ann Arbor Newspapers 1975-1979, 5 folders (Box 1)
  - Michigan RDNA Legislation (Box 1)
  - University Record, 1975-1977, 2 folders (Box 1)
- Correspondence, Minutes, and Articles
  The Correspondence, Minutes, and Articles series includes correspondence and minutes from the committees concerned with the recombinant DNA discussion as well as academic articles written on the controversy.
  - Concerning Recombinant DNA Issues (Box 1)
  - March 14, 1975-December 15, 1977, undated, 15 folders (Box 1)
- Governor's Task Force
  The Governor's Task Force series includes material from Governor William Milliken's Task Force on High Technology Industry, particularly the Subcommittee on Molecular Biology. Perhaps the most significant component of this series is the reports issued by the Task Force.
  - Alan Fischer (Box 2)
  - Ann Arbor Research Collective on Hi-Tech 1981-1982 (Box 2)
  - Department of Defense Sponsored Research at UM: Bret Eynon (Box 2)
  - Draft Reports on Controls and Letters (Box 2)
  - Michigan Environmental Laws -- DNR, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Michigan Hi-Tech Task Force Committee Memberships (Box 2)
  - Michigan: Industrial Development (Box 2)
  - Michigan Senate Bills 515 and 517 (Box 2)
  - Military Research 1981-1982, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Military Research at Michigan (Box 2)
  - Molecular Biology Task Force Minutes and Meeting Announcements (Box 2)
  - Molecular Biology Task Force: Notes and Miscellaneous Documents (Box 2)
  - Notes on Conversations (Box 2)
  - Notes and Phone Numbers (Box 2)
  - Position Paper (Box 2)
  - Proposals for Research Institutes, Michigan Research Corporation (Box 2)
  - Report to Governor's Task Force, Wright, Fischer 1982 (Box 2)
  - Report of Molecular Biology Committee 1982 (Box 2)
  - Reports (Box 2)
  - Reports of Molecular Biology Subcommittee Members (Box 2)
  - Senate Assembly Act 1981 (Box 2)
  - Susan Wright -- Report on Status of Controls (Box 2)
  - Trilateralism in Michigan (Box 2)
- Topical
  The Topical series contains material from a variety of different topics, including Committees A, B, and C, Regents' meetings, and lectures.
  - Ad Hoc Appraisal of Biological Research Review Committee 1977 (Box 2)
  - Ad Hoc Group Discussions (Box 2)
  - Ad Hoc Review of Recombinant DNA 1977-1978 (Box 2)
  - Biological Sciences Meeting 1976 (Box 2)
  - Board of Regents Statements 1975-1976 (Box 2)
  - Committee A -- Request for Renovations of Laboratories 1975 (Box 2)
  - Committee C -- Reports, Notes, Minutes (Box 2)
  - Committees/Organizational Charts (Box 2)
  - Correspondence with UM Officials 1975-1976 (Box 2)
  - Critique of Report of Committee B 1976 (Box 2)
  - Documents Relevant to Neidhardt's Statement at Regents Meeting 1976 (Box 2)
  - DNA Committees Chronology 1975-1977 (Box 2)
  - Drafts of Critique of Report of Committee B 1976 (Box 2)
  - Endorsements of Critique of Committee B Report (Box 2)
  - Folk Committee 1975 (Box 2)
  - "Important Questions to Answer" (Box 2)
  - Letter to Community 1976 (Box 2)
  - Microbiology 554 (Box 2)
  - MIT Institute Archives Materials (Box 2)
  - Nominations of Members, Committee B, Report Critique, Response to Critique (Box 2)
  - Notes on David Jackson's Talk to Philosophy Class 1976 (Box 2)
  - Notes on Decision Making at UM 1976-1979 (Box 2)
  - Other Correspondence on UM Events (Box 2)
  - Planning for Forum on Recombinant DNA Research (Box 2)
  - Roy Curtiss: Talk at UM Forum 1976 (Box 2)
  - Regents Meetings
    - April 15, 1976 (Box 2)
    - May 12, 1978 (Box 2)
  - Response of Committee A to Critique of Report of Committee B (Box 2)
  - Senate Assembly Correspondence 1976 (Box 2)
  - UM Community Response (Box 2)
  - University Views on Recombinant DNA Issue 1975-1977 (Box 2)
    (includes one cassette tape and official reports)
  - Values Seminar (Box 2)
Related Material
Related Material: For additional material relating to the recombinant DNA debate, researchers may be interested in the records of the Collegiate Institute for Values and Science also held at the Bentley Historical Library.